Guide to the North Star Mining Company and Associated Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
North Star Mining Company and associated records
1853-1959
WA MSS S-1322
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
109.5
(251 boxes) + 11 broadside folders
The records document quartz mining in Nevada County, California. The collection consists of the corporate records of the North Star Mining Company, Gold Hill Mining Company, and other Grass Valley companies. The collection contains deeds and maps of the area, as well as printed material on Grass Valley and mining. A smaller quantity of material documents mining in other areas and may have been the property of James D. Hague, one of the largest Grass Valley investors.
North Star Mining Company
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased with money from the William Robertson Coe fund from Alta California Bookstore in 1966.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 120-124: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 12-19a and 95-97: Restricted fragile material. Restricted until conservation work has been completed. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
HISTORY OF MINING IN GRASS VALLEY, NEVADA COUNTY, CALIFORNIA
Nevada County, in northwestern California, is one of the gold bearing regions discovered in the mid-nineteenth century. Early miners panned for gold, changing to hydraulic mining (washing the gold out of near surface rock) as the river beds were exhausted. Eventually hard rock mining, digging down into the bedrock, was the only profitable method of mining. In Nevada County veins of gold were found in quartz and the area became famous for quartz mining.
During the 1850s, miners worked individually or in small informal groups. The change from placer to hard rock mining was accompanied by a change to large incorporated companies and heavy machinery. By the 1860s, San Francisco investors were buying up mining claims and establishing corporate offices in San Francisco. Eventually many companies set up a second office in New York in order to trade on the eastern stock exchange. Most mining records in this collection date from this period.
The following time line chronicles the companies of Grass Valley, Nevada County. The names of companies which figure predominately in this collection have been capitalized. Most corporate names contained the phrase "Gold Mining Company," "Quartz Mining Company," or just "Mining Company; and often all three titles were used over time. Sometimes the names have been shortened for convenience.
1850 George McKnight discovers gold bearing quartz on GOLD HILL and George D. Roberts locates a claim near Ophir Hill. Gold is also found at Massachusetts Hill where the ROCKY BAR MINING COMPANY, a "joint-labor association" begins mining.
1851 A party of Frenchmen discovers gold at Lafayette hill, later the site of the NORTH STAR.
Nevada County is organized and Nevada City is chosen as county seat.
1852 NORTH STAR and NEW YORK HILL MINES are first worked.
1854 Ophir Hill mining claims are purchased by EMPIRE MINING COMPANY.
1855 Grass Valley incorporates.
1856 Mount Hope Company works the ROCKY BAR MINE until financial ruin in 1858.
1858 A. Chavanne and associates purchase the ROCKY BAR MINE and work it until 1866.
1860s Due to "Washoe fever," mining decreases in Grass Valley as people rush to Nevada.
1861-62 Many mines in Grass Valley flood due to hard winter. Steam power is used to operate pumps and clear the mines.
1863 ROCKY BAR MINING COMPANY incorporates.
EMPIRE MINE is sold to new investors who begin operations in 1865.
1866 MASSACHUSETTS HILL partnership forms.
1867 NORTH STAR GOLD MINING COMPANY incorporates. San Francisco capitalists buy the mine.
1871 NEW YORK HILL GOLD MINING COMPANY incorporates.
1877 GOLD HILL MINING COMPANY incorporates. Evidence exists of a company working the mine and operating a mill as early as 1856.
ROCKY BAR reorganizes under Henry Silvester and moves its corporate office to Grass Valley.
1878 Scadden Flat Gold Mining Company forms.
1879 TRIBUTE MINING COMPANY incorporates. Their claims are on New York Hill.
1880 TRIBUTE attempts without success to sell its mine to George Fletcher and then Black Lead Mining Company.
1883 GOLD HILL rents its mine to Scotia Gold Mining Company of New York.
1884 North Star mine, which has fallen idle, is bought by NORTH STAR MINING COMPANY, a company formed by W. B. Bourn and Grass Valley business interests. The new company buys machinery from the Scotia Company, paying with company stock.
GRASS VALLEY WATER COMPANY incorporates. The EMPIRE COMPANY helps finance this company which provided the water to power the mine's machinery.
1887 NORTH STAR establishes a transfer agency in New York to facilitate trading on Wall Street.
1889 MASSACHUSETTS HILL adopts by-laws. There is a flood of capital to the mines around Massachusetts Hill.
1890 Floods in the NORTH STAR mine brings work to a halt.
1891 Wolf Creek Quartz Mining Company incorporates.
James D. Hague begins investing in the ROCKY BAR. He was a major force in Grass Valley mining, serving as president and majority stockholder of the North Star; from this position he bought into most of the other mines represented in this collection.
1893 ROCKY BAR taken over by Hague and his associates.
GRANITE HILL MINING & DEVELOPMENT COMPANY forms or starts working their mine.
1894 NORTH STAR acquires other mines and raises capital for development work. The following mines or areas are absorbed by the company: Boston Ravine, Bowery, Dipper, Great Britain patent, James K. Byrne patent, Magenta, MASSACHUSETTS HILL, L. W. Kitts claim, Lode Star, NEW YORK HILL, Polkinghorn, Ford and Reilly property, Southern Patent, STOCKBRIDGE, Star Placer, Walworth ground, Watt ground, Wickes Field. By the beginning of twentieth century North Star controls most of the mining companies represented in this collection.
NORTH STAR sued by Carson City Gold & Silver Mining Company over Irish American claim.
NORTH STAR begins planning for an electrical generating plant run by water. A. D. Foote, a mining engineer, is hired to supervise the project.
1895 TRIBUTE attempts to sell its property to C. H. Kingsley.
Scadden Flat mine is bought up by Hague, Fred Searls, Thomas Marshall and others and becomes part of NORTH STAR.
1896 NORTH STAR reincorporates and acquires more mining companies and properties.
Hague, A. D. Foote, Fred Searls, and Thomas Marshall become shareholders of the TRIBUTE, and eventually the mine becomes part of NORTH STAR.
1898 New York becomes the de facto corporate office for the NORTH STAR. North Star buys out the GRASS VALLEY WATER COMPANY.
1899 NORTH STAR reincorporates in New Jersey.
1903 Hague becomes director and sole managing director of GOLD HILL, which then ceases to exist.
1911 North Star, through its agent J. M. O'Brien, buys out CHAMPION MINES.
1926 Under the supervision of A. D. Foote, deep development work begins in the NORTH STAR mine.
1928 Ernest Howe, geologist and treasurer of North Star, is sent to inspect the MASSACHUSETTS HILL. In 1929, Howe advises shutting down operations.
1929 NORTH STAR merges with the EMPIRE, which is in turn bought by the Newmont Mining Company of New York.
ROCKY BAR property, by this time, is owned by Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research
1943 The Newmont Company comes close to closing down operations in Grass Valley.
1956 NORTH STAR mines shut down because water, used to operate the mines, is too expensive.
1958 New Verde, which acquired the NORTH STAR and EMPIRE mines, auctions off the properties and equipment.
1959 NORTH STAR power plant machinery is sold at public auction.
1961 New Verde deeds the power plant site and Pelton Wheel to Grass Valley for a mining museum.
CHART OF MERGERS OF GRASS VALLEY MINING COMPANIES
-----------------------------------------------Rocky Bar Co.(1850) -----------------------------------------------------# ------Empire Co. (1854)-----------------------Mount Hope (1854) ---------#-------------------------------------------# ---------#------------------------------------Chavanne & Co. (1858) ---------#-------------------------------------------# ---------#------------------------------------Rocky Bar Co. (1863) ---------#-------------------------------------------# ---------#-------------------North Star (1867)-------# ---------#------------------------#------------------# ------Original Empire-------------#------------------# ------Mill & Mining---------------#------------------# -------(1880s)--------------------#------------------# ---------#------------------------#------------------# ---------#----------------------(1893)---------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1894)-----------Magenta ---------#----------------------(1894)-----------Stockbridge (1860s) ---------#----------------------(1894)-----------Massachusetts Hill (1866) ---------#----------------------(1894)-----------New York Hill (1871) ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1890s)----------Central North Star ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1895)-----------Scadden Flat (1878) ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1896)-----------Tribute (1879) ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1898)-----------Grass Valley Water Co. (1884) ------Empire Mines----------------# ------& Investment----------------# -------(ca. 1902)-----------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1903)-----------Gold Hill (1877) ---------#------------------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------#----------------------(1911)-----------Champion Mines ---------#------------------------# ---------#------------------------# ---------------------# ---------------------# ---------------------# --------------Empire Star Mines -------------------(1929) ---------------------# ---------------------# ---------------------# -----------New Verde Mines Company ----------------(pre-1959)
Scope and Contents
The North Star Mining Company and Associated Records document quartz mining in Nevada County, California. The collection spans the dates 1853 to 1963, but the bulk of the material falls in the period 1860 to 1900. These are primarily the records of the North Star Mining Company, which by 1900 had absorbed most of the other companies represented in this collection. A few mining records document activity outside of Grass Valley and may have belonged to James D. Hague, one of the largest investors in Grass Valley. Printed material from the 1960s seems to have been the property of twentieth century mine officers.
The collection is arranged in twelve series. The first ten representing individual companies; Series XI contains smaller record groups documenting mining in Grass Valley and other California counties, while Series XII consists of printed material about Grass Valley and mining.
Series I-X are alphabetically arranged by company name, and each is divided by record type. Executive Records documents the incorporation and management of a company, such as minutes of directors' meetings, correspondence between the directors and mine superintendent, and stock documents. Operation Records contains reports on the overall management of the mine while Ore and Bullion Records, Financial Records, Pay Roll Records, and Inventory Records, consist of reports on a specific area of operations. Other Material contains photographs and material related to the company. A detailed schedule of document types and their arrangement appears in Appendix I.
Series I. Empire Mines and Investment Company: Sometime prior to 1902 this company was known as Original Empire Mill and Mining Company, in 1929 it merged with the North Star mines to become the Empire Star Mines Company Ltd. The bulk of the papers (Box 1) document Empire's purchase of land and mineral rights in and around Grass Valley over the period 1900-20. President William B. Bourn often acted as an intermediary in these real estate transactions. There are two contemporary photographic postcards of workers in the Empire mine.
Series II. Empire Star Mines Company Ltd.: This company was formed by the merger of the Empire Mines and Investment Company and the North Star Company. There is very little material on this company, except for contracts from 1929-30 regulating the operation of the mine and court documents from the 1930s (Box 3, folders 62-63 and 64-65). The Gladys-Belle Mine report (folder 66) contains a concise history of the area as well as a 1913 map of the Grass Valley mining district which shows many of the mines represented in this collection.
Series III. Gold Hill Mining Company: Incorporated in 1877, Gold Hill was taken over by North Star in 1903. Executive Records (Boxes 3-9) are extensive and span the entire period of the company's existence. The by-laws describe the corporate structure, while the minutes note the founders, officers, and directors of Gold Hill. The minutes record decisions on contracts, machinery, finances, and mine operations, and include copies of important documents.
Correspondence consists of letters received by and sent from Gold Hill's San Francisco office and letters received by and sent from by its Grass Valley office covering the period 1890-1902. The letters to the corporate office in San Francisco (Boxes 4-7) are from stockholders and various other parties, but mostly from mine superintendents to the president or secretary. [For a list of Gold Hill's corporate officers, see Appendix 1.] The stockholders letters of 1890 concern assessments, while the superintendent's letters discuss construction of buildings, laying railroad tracks, timbering the mine, flooding in the mine, and the hiring of J. H. Hammond, a consulting engineer. Many letters refer to drafts drawn and record keeping; they indicate a constant stream of reports from Gold Hill's Grass Valley office to the corporate headquarters. Machinery and supplies are also addressed throughout the 1890s. In 1891 management discusses business with Risdon Iron & Locomotive Works and the Grass Valley Water Company. Letters in 1892-93 note financial transactions and imply Gold Hill is inactive. The correspondence of 1896 shows a burst of activity, with the construction of a power plant, purchase of machinery from Stanley Electric Manufacturing, and establishment of a branch line from the Nevada County Electric Power Company. Two years later letters mention the increase of capital stock, high costs of supplies, "bad ore," and wranglings with North Star over boundaries. The letters from Grass Valley are frequently accompanied in the files by a copy of the secretary's or president's replies.
Letters sent from the San Francisco office (Boxes 6-8, folders 87-163), the bulk of which are filed with letters received in San Francisco, are mostly from the president to the superintendent. Letters for the last years, 1900-03, focus on the mine's progress and eventual attempts to sell it.
The final two groups of letters are the correspondence of the Grass Valley office (Boxes 8-9, folders 164-92). Letters received at Grass Valley are usually from the president to the superintendent. Frequently these are duplicates of letters found in the San Francisco files (Box 6-8, folders 87-163), but the Grass Valley office files is a more complete record. In 1899-1900 the letters focus on the construction of an electric hoist, machinery, supplies, and mining employees and tributers. [Tribute, or contract work, as used in Grass Valley and defined by the Oxford English Dictionary, is "The proportion of ore raised or its value paid to miners by owners in exchange for labour." During the first decades of mining in Grass Valley, tributary relationships were common in Grass Valley. Tributers worked side by side with company employees. Over time they were phased out, though never completely eliminated.] A discussion of the Minna Mine controlled by Sherwood Hopkins of the Gambetta Mining and Milling Company (Grub Gulch, Madera County), ranges over this period and into 1902. Mine development is a constant topic, and the president often suggests the superintendent consult Mr. Foote of North Star. Letters sent from Grass Valley office are generally copies of letters found in the San Francisco files (Boxes 4-7), but this set contains material for 1894, the one gap in the San Francisco set.
Information on the Gold Hill's capital and investors spans the life of the company (see Box 9, folders 201-10). The stock ledger, organized by stockholder, records when certificates were canceled or issued; similar information is listed chronologically in the transfer journal. Assessments, (how much, when, and who paid) are noted in a separate ledger.
Gold Hill's Operation Records only cover the latter period of company's history, however the weekly reports for 1896-1902 are nearly complete (see Boxes 10-11, folders 213-44; parts of 1899 and 1902 missing). These reports note shafts being worked, amount of ore and waste hoisted, number of feet progressed, and number of men employed. This data is broken down into further detail, such as ore from stopes or drifts and men on contracts or employed by the company. Information on assays, production of sulphurets, and bullion is recorded in monthly reports for 1896-97 (Box 10, folders 211-12). A book of amalgam accounts (folder 275) reports the processing of ore and the quantity of amalgam retrieved.
Financial Records (Boxes 12-20) for Gold Hill Mining Company are substantial. Ledgers and cash books exist for 1877-1903. Ledgers contain separate accounts of assessments, bullion, building improvements, electric power, repairs, and many other services and supplies. Cash books record similar information but are organized chronologically instead of by account. A column in the cash book records the ledger page on which the data is noted or the number of the draft used to pay the bill. Monthly statements (folders 282-87), like the ledgers, list expenses and earnings by categories. Trial balances are also linked to the ledgers; each expense includes a ledger page citation. Tribute statements list quantity of ore each tributer mined, value of the gold, and cost of the services and supplies provided by the Gold Hill company.
Superintendent's statements and drafts (Boxes 12-19A) are a monthly package of reports the Gold Hill superintendent prepared from monthly bills and reports. From 1897 to 1902 most packages consist of: receipts; mine and mill storehouse reports (noting the amount of supplies used and on hand and their value); pay roll records (noting name, occupation, pay rate, amounts paid); and starting in 1898, statements of expenses (data similar to monthly statements).
Most of the material which would be filed in Gold Hill's Pay Roll Records and Inventory Records is in the superintendent's statements and drafts (Boxes 12-19A). There are two separate inventory ledgers dating from 1897-1900 noting quantity and usage for supplies and wood.
Series IV. Granite Hill Mining & Development Co.: The Granite Hill Company began operating in 1893, and although most records date from the 1890s, they are fragmentary. Several agreements and court actions concern Martin Ford, an early investor (Box 20). The journal of T. F. Phillips (Box 21, folder 490), dating from 1897-99, contains daily, though terse, descriptions of activity at the mine: "fixing pumps," "started Mitchell & Thomas in [underhand] stope," "all hands laid off for Xmas." The weather is noted in almost every entry and three columns ("W"[aste], "M[mill or mining ?], "Q[uartz]) record routine data. Daily amalgam records for 1897 and 1899, recorded in brief statements, are at the back of this journal.
Series V. Grass Valley Water Company: This company was started with financing from the Original Empire Mill and Mining Company in 1884, but was purchased by the North Star in 1898, who had been managing the company as early as 1894. The Grass Valley Water Company provided water power to the mines.
Executive Records (Boxes 21-22) documents the founding of the Grass Valley Water Company and its early financial troubles. The 1889 by-laws were drafted when the water company finally settled its financial affairs with the Empire Company. The original by-laws can be found in the volume of minutes (folder 500). Minutes also contain copies of agreements and the 1899 "Declaration and judgement for Dissolution." Folders for copies of minutes and material from meetings contain papers needed to vote for directors: stockholder lists, ballots, and tallies.
Although there is some information on the 1890s, the majority of Grass Valley Water Company's stock documents cover 1885-89 (Box 22, folders 525-33). A ledger, listing stocks by name of holder, and the transfer journal, noting the sale of shares, record the offer to Empire of company stock in return for a loan. Instead, James D. Hague bought the shares in 1889 making North Star part owner of the water company.
The daily water supply and log book is the major record in Operation Records (folder 534). Covering the period 1888-96, it contains narrative reports on the water pressure, condition of the reservoir, and supply to consumers. For instance, "main Reservoir going down assumption being North Star was using more than 250 [inches] water" indicates how precarious the relationship was between the Grass Valley Water Company and the mines. Separate reports of North Star's water consumption for 1894-97 are filed in Series VIII (Boxes 57-66, folders 1408-1502).
Financial Records (Boxes 22-23) for the Grass Valley Water Company are sparse and fragmentary. The ledger and journal end in 1889, although there are some annual statements for the 1890s. There is extensive information on financial arrangements between Grass Valley Water Company and the Empire. Accounts with Empire Company (folder 542), organized by expense, record what bills Empire paid on behalf of the water company. This is followed by an account of money North Star owed to the water company, yet paid to Empire in return for its loan.
Series VI. Massachusetts Hill Mining Company: Massachusetts Hill (Box 24) adopted by-laws in 1889, but there was probably an earlier incorporation or working association. The mine was absorbed by North Star in 1894. Massachusetts Hill mine was finally deemed unworthy of further work by Ernest Howe in 1929.
The founding and structure of the Massachusetts Hill Company is well documented by the certificate of incorporation and the by-laws. Other records are insufficient to document the operation of the mine.